Finding Aid for the M.A. Zeitlin Papers LSC.0353
UCLA Library Special Collections
M.A. Zeitlin papers
1915-1993
UCLA Library Special Collections
Zeitlin, M.A. (Marion Albert)
LSC.0353
1 unknown (5 boxes and 24 oversize boxes)
M.A. Zeitlin (1899-1993) was the chair of the Department of Spanish and Italian at UCLA. He founded the departmental program in Portuguese, helped to develop a curriculum in Latin American studies, and was a member of the initial committee on Latin American Studies. The collection consists of Zeitlin's curricular files, correspondence, photographs, manuscripts, and publications and research files as well as the professional papers of his wife, Frances K. Zeitlin.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nancy Eaton, 1994.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942340583606533
Biography
Zeitlin was born on August 29, 1899 in Chicago; moved to Arizona and attended the University of Arizona, BA (1918), MA (1920), Stanford University; continued study of French in Brussels and at the Sorbonne; accepted teaching position at University of California Southern Branch in 1925; moved to Berkeley two years later, earning a Ph.D. in romance languages with Spanish as a major field from the University of California at Berkeley in 1931; returned to UCLA in the same year as an assistant professor, later becoming chair of the Department of Spanish and Italian, as well as a full professor; founded the departmental program in Portuguese, helped to develop a curriculum in Latin American studies, and was a member of the initial committee on Latin American Studies; in 1967 he was named Comendador of the Ordem do Infante Dom Henrique by the Portuguese government and in 1968 awarded the title of Oficial of the Ordem Nacional do Cruzeiro do Sul; he was awarded the UCLA Medal for Distinguished Service in 1980; after the death of his wife Zell in 1967, he married Frances Kirschenbaum, the medieval and renaissance bibliographer at the UCLA University Research Library; Zeitlin died on September 8, 1993.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of curricular files, correspondence, photographs, manuscripts of M.A. Zeitlin's publications and research files, and professional papers of his wife, Frances K. Zeitlin.
Related Material
A Collection of Manuscripts (reproduction) in Spanish (Collection 1264). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Language teachers -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Manuscripts for publication; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Spanish and Portuguese--Faculty -- Archives; Zeitlin, Frances K.--Archives.; Zeitlin, M.A. (Marion Albert)
- Correspondence, Research Material, etc.
  - Card Catalog 1, n.d. / v.d.
    - A - Alo. (Box 1)
    - Alp - Bam. (Box 2)
    - Ban - Cat. (Box 3)
    - Cau - Co. (Box 4)
    - Cr - D. (Box 5)
    - E - Esq. (Box 6)
    - Est - Ge. (Box 7)
    - Gi - La. (Box 8)
    - Le - Meq. (Box 9)
    - Mer - Pan. (Box 10)
    - Pao - P. (Box 11)
    - Q - R. (Box 12)
    - S - Ta. (Box 13)
    - Te - V. (Box 14)
    - W - Z. (Box 15)
  - Card Catalog (AYALA), n.d. / v.d.
    - A - Cons. (Box 17)
  - Card Catalog 2 (AYALA), n.d. / v.d.
    - Citations. (Box 16)
    - Cont. - E. (Box 18)
    - F - O. (Box 19)
    - P - S. (Box 20)
    - T - Z and notes. (Box 21)
  - Card Catalog 3, n.d. / v.d.
    - O.S. general - O.S. vocabulary. (Box 22)
    - Spain - Comparative. (Box 23)
    - Comparative - end. Includes notes, etc. (Box 24)
  - Personal and Professional Correspondence
    - Students, to 1958 n.d. / v.d.
      - General. (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - A - C. (Box 25, Folder 2)
      - D - G. (Box 25, Folder 3)
      - H - M. (Box 25, Folder 4)
      - Mc - N. (Box 25, Folder 5)
      - O - P. (Box 25, Folder 6)
      - Q - R (R only). (Box 25, Folder 7)
      - S (only). (Box 25, Folder 8)
      - T - Z. (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Students - Celebration of Spanish Department of Yesteryear, 1964 retirement year., after 1958. n.d. / v.d. 1981 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Students, After 1958 n.d. / v.d.
      - A (only). (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - B - C. (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - D - F. (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - G - K. (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - L - M. (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - Mc - R. (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - S (only). (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - T - Z. (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Colleagues and Friends, to 1945 n.d. / v.d.
      - A - B. (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - C - G. (Box 27, Folder 2)
      - H - M. (Box 27, Folder 3)
      - T - Z. (Box 27, Folder 4)
        Scope and Contents
        Folder contains a photograph of Zeitlin circa 1936.
    - Colleagues and Friends, 1945-1956 n.d. / v.d.
      - A - B. (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - C - D. (Box 27, Folder 6)
      - E - G. (Box 27, Folder 7)
      - H - J. (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - K - O. (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - P - Z. (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Colleagues and Friends, 1956- n.d. / v.d.
      - A (only). (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - B (only). (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - C - D. (Box 28, Folder 6)
      - E - G. (Box 28, Folder 7)
      - H - M. (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - N - Z. (Box 28, Folder 9)
        Folder contains a 1980 photograph of Zeitlin, recipient of UCLA Medal for Distinguished Service.
    - Professional UCLA Faculty. (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Professional, n.d. / v.d.
      - A - C. (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - D - G. (Box 29, Folder 3)
      - H - M. (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - M - N. (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - O - P. (Box 29, Folder 6)
      - R - S. (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - T - Z. (Box 29, Folder 8)